Hey friends, my name is Deepak Jain and I
am the founder of Infinity Gas LLP.
Health insurance is
purchased so that it can be claimed
without any hassle or problem at the time of need.
Claims under health insurance can be
claimed in two basic ways. To
claim a cashless claim, the
patient simply needs to go to the hospital, get
treatment there, and
submit their policy documents and an ID proof to the TPA desk at the hospital. The TPA completes the rest of the formalities by
coordinating with the insurance company. To
avail treatment on a cashless basis, the
client does not have to pay any amount.
Many times, it happens that the client says
that the hospital where he wants treatment is
not on the company's cashless panel.
It is also possible that the
client is in a location anywhere in India
where cashless
facility is not available. In such cases, a
claim can be made from the insurance company through reimbursement.
Now, many times, clients say that they have not paid any amount.
Documents have been submitted
to the company to get reimbursement but either there is a lot of
delay in it or
many times a lot of requirements come, a
lot of documents are asked for or the
claim is sent for investigation, so keeping in mind
all these scenarios, on
11 June 2020,
IRDAI i.e. Insurance Regulatory
and Development Authority of India has
issued some guidelines to all the insurance companies keeping in mind the interests of the client
and within these guidelines,
a provision has also been given regarding claim settlement,
so we are going to discuss these guidelines in today's
video,
so these guidelines are claim
settlement provision for panel interest, that is,
all the insurance companies have been told
that if there is a delay in claim settlement, then
they will have to bear some penalty,
which will be at the rate of 2%, so let us try
to understand how this whole process is completed, the
company can settle and reject a claim
further in this case also within 30 days  From
the date of receipt of the last necessary
document, so first of all the insurance company has the
right to
accept or reject the claim as
per the policy document or
whatever is the criteria of the policy within 30
days from the date of receipt of the last
necessary document. So on the day you have
submitted the document to the company,
after that the insurance company has to
settle the claim within 30 days.
Suppose if the insurance company has
asked for any retirement in it, then on the day you
submitted that requirement, after that the
insurance company has to settle that claim within the next 30 days.
In case of delay in payment of any
claim, the company shall be liable to pay
interest to the policy holder from the
date of receipt of the last necessary
document to the payment of claim at a rate of 0.5
percent or less than the bank rate. So here
IRDAI has given these guidelines to all the insurance companies that
whenever you have a
claim
You have to pay this claim within 30 days from the date of receipt of the documents.
But if you do not pay the claim, then
you will be liable to pay 2% rate of
interest whichever is
2% more than the prevailing bank rate of interest for that financial year. Where the
circumstances of an unclaimed claim
warrant and investigation in the opinion of the
company, it should be initiated and completed such
investigation and the initialist should be given in other
cases not later than 30 days from the date of
receipt of the last necessary document. In
such cases, the company should settle or reject the
claim within 45 days from the date of
receipt of the last necessary document. So
here
IRDAI has given this guideline to all the insurance companies
that whenever you receive the claim
documents,
you have to settle the claim within 30 days. Suppose
if any document is missing in those claim documents
or any  Other documents are also being
requested, which you will have to
exchange with the hospital. For example, IPD
documents are requested from the hospital.
IPD documents are those
documents that when a patient is
admitted to the hospital,
a cardboard is kept with them, and their record of every half an
hour and every hour is
written there. These
documents have to be obtained from the hospital,
so these documents are requested. Now,
when you submit these documents to the insurance company, then within
days the insurance
company has to settle the claim.
Now, sometimes it happens that the
insurance company says that we
also need to investigate this claim. Now,
investigation means that wherever
you were treated, the
insurance company can arrange for either its own
doctors or third-party vendors,
and they can
also be sent to your home, they can
also be sent to your neighborhood, and they
can also be sent to the hospital where you received the treatment.  And in such
cases where the case has been sent for investigation, the
insurance company has to
accept or reject the claim within a maximum of 45 days.
In case of delay beyond the stated 45
days, the company shall be liable to pay
interest to the policy holder at a rate
of 2% above the bank rate from the date of
receipt of the last necessary document to the date
of payment of the claim. In such cases
which are sent for investigation,
whenever the
last claim documents have been submitted by the client
and the claim has been sent for investigation
and in such a case, if the delay takes
more than 45 days, then the rate of interest at the rate of 2% will have to be paid from the time the last
document was submitted by the client till the
delay occurs.
This 2% will be above the bank rate, which means
it will be two percent more than the rate of interest defined by the bank for the financial year.  Let
us understand that bank
rate shall mean the rate fixed by the
Reserve Bank of India (RBI) at the
beginning of the financial year in which case the policy due.
So, as we have already
discussed, bank rate means
whatever rate of interest is defined by RBI, that is, Reserve Bank of
India, at the time of the start of the financial year.
This rate of interest will be 2%
more than that. Note 2: Insurance:
An important note has also been given in this circular. The
close shall be suitably
modified by the insurance company based on the amendment.
So here the insurance company has
also been told that if they want, they can make
some modifications in this proper close,
other than the relevant provisions of
Protection of Policy Holders' Interest
Regulation 2017. But here it has also been said
that changes can be made in this particular circular only keeping in mind the Policy Holders' Interest
Regulation Act 2017.
So hopefully  Hey
friends, you must have liked the circular issued by IRDAI to all the insurance companies for the client benefit or
for the protection of consumers,
or you must have liked this knowledge video,
if you liked this video then
please do like it, if you have
any feedback or comment related to this video then please do
tell us by commenting in the comment box,
if you want to share
this video with your friends, relatives, sorry, gents fertility,
then please do share it,
friends, an important thing is to subscribe to the channel
and friends,
if you
want to make your career in the live general or health insurance sector
or want to
buy a live general or health insurance policy for yourself or your family,
then you can coordinate
with our team on the numbers written in the description,
so friends, thank
you, thank you so much for watching this video,
thank you